in order for plants to grow they need
imports of carbon dioxide
water and energy
the chemical process by which plants use
these resources to manufacture glucose
the building blocks of plants is called
photosynthesis
in the process oxygen gases produced
as a byproduct
the energy for photosynthesis originates
in the Sun
and arrives at the earth as sunlight
this light has both a wave and a
particle nature
the particles or photons are the
smallest units of light
photons oscillates along a path which is
measured
as wavelengths
the light emitted from the Sun contains
photons in a wide spectrum of
wavelengths
called the electromagnetic spectrum
photosynthetic organisms use only a
small portion of the electromagnetic
spectrum
called visible light
photosynthetic organisms contain
pigments that facilitate the capture of
wavelengths of light
in the visible light range
the color of a pigment comes from the
wavelengths of light reflected
plants appear green because they reflect
yellow and green wavelengths of light
red and blue wavelengths of light are
absorbed by these pigments
and provide the energy that is used for
photosynthesis
within eukaryotic photosynthetic
organisms also known as
photoautotropes
the chemical reactions of photosynthesis
occur within plant cells
in specialized structures known as
chloroplast
photosynthesis consists of two sets of
reactions
the light dependent reactions and the
Calvin cycle
within the chloroplast are small disc
like structures
called thylakoids which are
surrounded by a fluid-filled space
called the stroma
the reactions that synthesize glucose
the Calvin cycle
occur in the stroma
the light dependent reactions occur in
the thylakoid
it is here that conversion of light
energy to chemical energy
is initiated
in most photosynthetic organisms thylakoid
contain pairs a photosystems
called photosystem one and photosystem
two
that work in tandem to produce the
energy that will later be used in the
stroma
to manufacture sugars
the photosystems of the thylakoid
consist of a network
of accessory pigment molecules and
chlorophyll
the molecules that absorb the photons of
light
within the pigment molecules the absorbed
light energy
excites electrons to a higher state
photosystems will channel the
excitation energy
gathered by the pigment molecules to a
reaction center chlorophyll molecule
which will then pass the electrons to a
series of proteins
located on the final thylakoid membrane
photons of light strike photosystems
1&2 simultaneously
we will examine what happens with the
photon striking photosystem
two first
the energized electrons are passed from
the reaction center of photosystem two
to an electron transport chain
the electrons lost by photosystem two
are replaced by a process called
photolysis
which involves the oxidation a water
molecule
producing free electrons and oxygen gas
well this oxygen gas is a byproduct of
photosynthesis
it is an important input to the
cellular respiration pathways
as electrons passed through the electron
transport chain
the energy from the electron is used to
pump hydrogen ions from the stroma
to the thylakoid creating a
concentration gradient
this gradient powers a protein called
ATP synthases
which phosphorylate ADP to form
ATP
the low-energy electrons leaving
photosystem two
are shuttled to photosystem one
within photosystem one low energy electrons
are reenergized
and are passed through an electron
transport chain where they are used to
reduce the electron carrier
NADP+ to NADPH
when the chloroplast is receiving a
steady supply of photons
NADPH and ATP molecules
are rapidly being provided to the
metabolic pathways
in the stroma
therefore the ATP and NADPH form during
the light dependent reactions
are used in the stroma to fuel the
Calvin cycle reactions
the Calvin cycle consists of a series of
reactions
that reduce carbon dioxide to produce
the carbohydrate
glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate
the cycle consists of three steps the
first of which
is carbon fixation
in this step carbon dioxide is attached
to ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate
resulting in a six carbon molecule that
splits into two
three carbon molecules
the second step is a sequence of
reactions using electrons from
NADPH and some of the ATP
to reduce carbon dioxide
in the final step ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate
is regenerated
for every three turns have the cycle 5
molecules of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate
are used to reform three molecules of
ribulose 1,5-bisphosphate
the remaining
glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate is then used
to make glucose
fatty acids or glycerol
it takes two molecules of
glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate
to make one molecule of glucose
phosphate
thus the Calvin cycle has to run six
times to produce one molecule
of glucose
these molecules can remove their
phosphate and add fructose to form
sucrose
the molecule plants used to transport
carbohydrates throughout their system
glucose phosphate is also the starting
molecule
for the synthesis of starch and
cellulose
plants produce sugars to use as storage
molecules
and structural components for their own
benefit
by utilizing the energy of the Sun along
with inputs of water and carbon dioxide
plants act as glucose factories
photosynthetic organisms are the primary
producers on glucose on the planet
they also produce oxygen gas as a
byproduct
and thus served as the foundation of life
providing food and oxygen
for the complex food webs on both land
and in the oceans